Leon Baiyu Shen Williams

E-mail leonbaiyu@gmail.com Website: leonbaiyu.github.io Telephone +44 780 689 6061

I am a recent Integrated MSci Chemical Physics with Work Placement graduate with first-class honours, from the University of Glasgow, with a strong skillset in physics, programming, and chemistry. I have experience in international scientific research, having spent a year working at the Diamond Light Source synchrotron, carrying out advanced chemical analytical and ultra-high vacuum techniques, and data analysis/acquisition. Furthermore, I have practical experience in programming, through my master's project, building and implementing agent-based models in Python to study economic systems through physics concepts. I am currently consolidating my software development skillset through independent study of key concepts including: documentation, system architecture, machine learning, and cloud computing.

Research Experience

Masters Thesis: Econophysics: Agent-based modelling of markets from kinetic theory of gases and Brownian motion

Sep 2022 – Apr 2023

- Applied physics concepts to study economic systems through agent-based models.
- Compared **kinetic theory of gases and Brownian motion** to individual interactions in markets through simulation of these agent-based models.
- Developed and adapted these models to produce emergent phenomena resembling economic systems, such as wealth distributions and stock price fluctuations.
- Using JavaScript to visualise interactive results on a webpage/server.
- Software was developed in Python and JupyterLab paired with GitHub and Docker.
- Incorporated a range of libraries including mesa-ABM, Scipy, Seaborn, Matplotlib, and Pandas alongside standard software development practices.

Year in Industry Work Placement – Diamond Light Source Ltd, Oxford Sep 2021 – Sep 2022

- Studied 2D materials including Graphene, and Graphene-like films in **ultra-high vacuum** (UHV) at the **Diamond Light Source synchrotron**.
- Chemical surface synthesis techniques (e.g. epitaxial growth), analysis techniques including X-ray and electron diffraction and spectroscopy, and microscopy.
- Data analysis for these techniques, often extracting signals from raw instrument data.
- Utilised scripting for automated data acquisition through instrument control using Jython
- High level data analysis involved Python, its associated libraries, and MATLAB, as well as FORTRAN for X-ray scattering calculations. Optimised using particle swarm optimization methods (PSO) run on the STFC high performance computing cluster.
- Balanced a workload of group and independent projects.
- Carried out research collaboration with/on behalf of groups in international universities including the Technical University of Munich.
- Involved in customer-facing tours of the facility and mentorship programme.
- Acquired technical skills for the **construction**, **mounting**, and **setup** of **UHV equipment**.

Publications: Using polycyclic aromatic hydrocarbons for graphene growth on Cu(111) under ultra-high vacuum – Appl. Phys. Lett. 121, 191603 (2022),

Adsorption structure of Iron Phthalocyanine and Titanyl Phthalocyanine on Cu(111) – Inorganica Chimica Acta 557, 121679 (2023),

Probing the role of surface termination in the adsorption of azupyrene on copper – Nanoscale (Pending Revision)

Education

2018 – 2023 Integrated MSci Chemical Physics - University of Glasgow, Scotland Grade: First Class

Relevant Modules: Nuclear & Particle Physics, Quantum Information, Atomic Systems, Electromagnetic Theory, Mathematical Methods, Quantum Mechanics, Thermal Physics, Solid State Physics

2012 – 2018 - James Gillespie's High School

Advanced Higher: Mathematics (A), Physics (A), Chemistry (A)

Higher: Mathematics (A), Physics (A), Chemistry (A), Computing (A), Biology (A)

National 5: Maths (A), Phys (A), Chem (A), Comp (A), Bio (A), Geo (A), French (A), Eng (A)

Technical Skills

My physics labs have been based around developing general experimental problem-solving:

• Applying **critical thinking and problem solving** to understand, design, execute, and evaluate in-depth experiments (e.g. Laser Interferometry, Polarisation).

Developing programming proficiencies:

- C, Python, FORTRAN and MATLAB.
- LiveCode, SQL, HTML and CSS, and project methodologies (Waterfall and Agile).
- Skilled in Windows and Unix-based operating systems.
- Optimisation algorithms (Particle Swarm Optimisation, Genetic Algorithm, Gradient Descent)
- Experienced in the use of **Docker**, **GitHub**, **Linux**, **high performance computer clusters**.

Practical Techniques:

- Chemical analytical (IR/NMR/UV/Vis/X-ray Spectroscopy, Mass Spectrometry, TLC, STM)
- X-ray and Electron Diffraction based techniques (XSW, LEED, ARPES, PhD)
- Ultra-high vacuum systems.

Other Experience and Extra-curricular activities

Camp Counselor - American Youth Foundation

Jun – Sep 2019

Responsible for organising events for large groups of all ages while simultaneously managing a cabin full of kids; planning and coordinating with other staff members a varying schedule that required forethought as well as the flexibility to react and adapt to situations that arose.

Research Assistant Placement at Edinburgh Royal Observatory

Nov - Dec 2017

Supporting the stakeholder engagement coordinator in the Space and Satellite innovation programme at Edinburgh Royal Observatory; selecting and writing concise accessible reports on topics of interest in astronomy (e.g. the potential of Lagrangian Points for stationing satellites).

Men's Captain - Glasgow University Ultimate Team

April 2020 – April 2021

- Managed a competitive team and played a primary leadership role in running a 100+ person University Sports Club.
- Led the team through novel challenges posed by the pandemic through forward-thinking, planning, and development of intake forecasts and risk assessments.

Home Projects

Apr – Sep 2020

- Self-directed and curiosity-driven study during interruption of formal education (COVID).
- Completed challenging projects such as reverse-engineering hardware (modifying Raspberry Pi, repurposing IR receiver from an old TV and repairing various technology), electroplating jewellery, heat treatment and hand crafting complex knife handles.
- Involved online research and utilising various resources such as online forums (e.g. StackOverflow for Python) for problem-solving, experimentation and learning.
- Employed practical skills including soldering and working with circuits and metal/woodwork.

Languages: English (Native), Mandarin (Spoken), French (National 5)